Guide to the Duncan Chaplin Lee and John Lee papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Duncan Chaplin Lee and John Lee Papers
1922-2011
MS 2062
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.10
21 containers
The collection consists of the personal papers of Duncan Chaplin Lee and his son, John Lee. Materials include Duncan Chaplin Lee's correspondence, writings, photographs, and biographical material regarding his personal and work life. Key within these materials are documents that chronicle Lee's evolving interest in Marxism-Leninism in the 1930s, his military service, and the events that surfaced after he was accused of espionage in 1948. This material was then used by historian Mark A. Bradley in his book, A Very Principled Boy: The Life of Duncan Lee, Red Spy and Cold Warrior. The papers of John Lee contain correspondence and research materials related to Duncan Chaplin Lee and the controversy surrounding his life and legacy. Materials range from 1927 to 2011.
Lee, Duncan Chaplin, 1913-1988
Lee, John Lightfoot, 1943-
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in two series and one addition: I. Duncan Chaplin Lee Papers, 1927-2010 II. John Lee Papers, 1998-2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of John L. Lee, 2016 and 2018.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the life of Duncan Chaplin Lee. Chronological correspondence and biographical materials in Series I represent the more substantive parts of the collection. The chronological correspondence documents Chaplin Lee's high school and college years. Particularly of note is correspondence between Duncan Chaplin Lee and his mother, Lucy Lee, between 1935 and 1937, which convey his evolving interest in Marxism and his affiliation with the Communist Party. The alphabetical correspondence involves mostly routine personal and work-related matters. There is little mention of the investigation and accusations levied against Chaplin Lee during the 1940s. Most of the clippings date from 1948 and involve Lee's testimony before the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC). Lee's writings on family, religion, and his career are included, as are his unfinished memoirs. Of specific interest is Chaplin Lee's extended essay entitled, "The Elizabeth Bentley Matter," where he repeatedly emphasizes his innocence. Photographs of Lee's childhood in China, his trips to Southeast Asia and Bermuda, and family portraits are among the photographs.
Series II consists of correspondence and research materials gathered by John Lee and his relatives to clear Lee's name of charges that he was a Soviet spy. Much of Series II documents John Lee's efforts (and his family's) to grapple with scholarship that utilized newly released documentation from the Soviet archives and declassified government documents to argue that Chaplin Lee committed espionage. Folders in Series II contain FBI files received by requests submitted by John Lee, Mark Bradley, or Bruce Craig—a researcher hired by the Lee family—under the Freedom of Information Act (FOIA). There is also an abundance of published materials that John Lee collected in conducting his own research into his father, Chaplin Lee. Series II also includes correspondence between members of the Lee family and scholars and historians who argued that Chaplin Lee was either guilty or innocent of espionage.
Users will find some duplications of materials in Series I and Series II. Some of the documents also appear in the Mark A. Bradley Collection on Duncan Chaplin Lee (MS 2063). After Duncan Chaplin Lee's death, the entire collection was obtained by John Lee, who loaned the collection to Mark A. Bradley for an extended period after 1999. Bradley organized and added to the materials during the process of conducting research for his book on Duncan Chaplin Lee. Bradley's influence on the collection is therefore evident in both series. Researchers will find Bradley's typed notes, transcriptions, and comments on Chaplin Lee's correspondence. At times, Bradley transcribed entire letters and attached them to the original. Bradley also made copies of Chaplin Lee's letters, FBI files on Chaplin Lee, and published materials and sent them to John Lee.
Biographical / Historical
Duncan Chaplin Lee
Duncan Chaplin Lee was born on December 19, 1913 in Anqing, China. His parents, United States citizens, served as missionaries in China. The family, which included a brother, Armistead, and a sister, Priscilla, moved back to the United States in 1927 and settled in Chatham, Virginia, near Lee's father's family. He attended Yale University and graduated in 1935. He was awarded a Rhodes Scholarship and finished his education at Christ Church, Oxford University. He received a Bachelor of Arts in jurisprudence in 1937 and a Bachelor of Civil Law degree in 1938. He also was a Sterling Fellow at Yale Law School from 1938 to 1939.
Lee worked as a lawyer at Donovan, Leisure, Newton, and Irvine from 1939 to 1942. From there, he joined the newly created Office of Strategic Services (OSS), a predecessor to the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA). He was subsequently commissioned a First Lieutenant in the Army. Lee worked as an aid to the director, General William "Wild Bill" Donovan and over time became the chief of the Secret Intelligence Branch. The OSS was disbanded in 1945 and Lee returned to practicing law. Immeditately after working for OSS, he served as counsel for the formation of the Civil Air Transport, a CIA backed project that airlifted supplies and troops to China, Taiwan, and Korea.
As a student at Oxford, he became interested in the ideas of the Communist Party. He saw it as a party that could stop the spread of fascism and joined the party as a secret member in 1939. It is believed that the Soviet Union recruited him as a spy shortly after joining the OSS. Over a period of three years he passed on political secrets to the Soviet government. When the war was concluded, former Soviet courier and operations assistant Elizabeth Bentley defected to the United States and implicated a number of Americans who served as sources. One of the sources she named when she testified to the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) on July 31, 1948 was Lee. Lee testified before HUAC denying the charges on August 10, 1948. He was believed due to a lack of written evidence to back up the charges, as well as his education and family background. When it was discovered in 1951 by the U.S. Army's Signal Intelligence Service's Venona Project that Lee was indeed a spy, the FBI was unable to press charges since the project materials were classified. Although he never faced any legal consequences, mounting questions about his trustworthiness from the accusations caused Lee to live outside of the United States after 1953. Lee died on April 15, 1988 in Toronto, Canada.
John Lee
John Lightfoot Lee was born on November 15, 1943 in Washington, D.C. He graduated with a Bachelor of Arts from the University of North Carolina in 1966 and a juris doctor degree from Harvard Law School in 1969. He practiced law in New York state for decades.
Custodial History
The papers were inherited by John Lee who took custody of them upon his father's death. John Lee loaned the collection to historian Mark A. Bradley for an extended period sometime after 1998 to enable Bradley to conduct research for his book on Duncan Chaplin Lee. Bradley then returned the collection to John Lee who donated the papers to Yale University Library in 2016.
Related Materials
Related Material: Mark A. Bradley Collection on Duncan Chaplin Lee (MS 2063).
Espionage; Cold War; United States -- Foreign policy; Communism -- 20th Century; Soviet Union; Lee, Duncan Chaplin, 1913-1988; Bentley, Elizabeth, 1908-1963; House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC); United States. Office of Strategic Services
- Duncan Chaplin Lee papers, 1922-2010; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I comprises the papers of Duncan Chaplin Lee. The chronological correspondence is primarily between Chaplin Lee and his family members, and covers his high school and college years at Yale and Oxford. Correspondents include his father, Edmund Jennings Lee, his mother, Lucy Chaplin Lee, and wife from 1938 to 1959, Ishbel Lee. Also in chronological correspondence are letters received by Chaplin Lee after receiving a Rhodes scholarship in 1935, and correspondence between Ishbel and Lucy Lee which frequently mentions Chaplin Lee. Alphabetical correspondence documents Lee's career after he left the Operation of Strategic Services (OSS) and covers topics such as his travel and passport restrictions, work-related matters, and family history and affairs. The biographical materials offer a range of letters and memorabilia that chronicle his life over time. Also present are Chaplin Lee's writings, photographs, and clippings.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged chronologically and alphabetically therein.
  - Correspondence--Chronological
    - 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Rhodes scholarship, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Ishbel Lee to Lucy Lee, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1939-1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Annotated transcriptions of chronological correspondence from Mark Bradley, 1931-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence--Alphabetical
    - Acheson, David, 1954-2008 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Adams, Philip, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Canada immigration, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cassels, Hamilton, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Celentano, Frank, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Clagett, Brice, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Corcoran, David, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Cox, Al (obituary), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Davies, John, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Doering, Jr., Otto, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Globe and Mail--Editor, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Hartfield, Henry, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - The Hemlock Society, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - "Intrepid Dinner", 1983 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Irvine, Ralstone, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Leary, William M., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Lee, Armistead, 1968-1984 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Lee, Ishbel, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Leisure, George S., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Levin, Alexandra Lee, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Pratt, John H., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - "Prich Letter", 1985 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Smith, Arnold, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Stockmayer, Walter H., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Tweedy, Mary Johnson, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Williams, Murat, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Winks, Robin, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Yorck, David, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Youngman, Jr., William, 1955-1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Biographical Materials
    - "Anking Revolution and Evacuation"--Edmund Lee, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Woodberry Forest and Yale University, 1928-1938 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Oxford University scrapbook, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Map of Oxford from scrapbook, 1937 (Box Box 3a)
    - Engagement announcement, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Wedding announcement, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Society of the Lees of Virginia, 1939-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Military record and decoration, 1940-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photo identification for House Committee on Military Affairs, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Burma, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Medical exams and records, 1945-1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Eric Sevareid memoirs, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Employment, 1946-1974 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Will and deed of trust, 1947-1954 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - House Un-American Affairs Committee, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Passports and travel documents, 1949-1981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Lee family history, 1949-2004 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - United States Army Reserve Commission, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Passport clearance, 1951-1954 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Driver's licenses, 1952-1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Divorce papers, 1958-1984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Addresses, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Insurance--Lee, McCarthy and DeRosa, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "The Chat--An Appreciation of Lucy Chaplin Lee", 1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Lucy Lee's memoir, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Application for permanent residence in Canada, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Why Have You Burned My House?" --Alexandra Lee Levin, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Debt owed by children, circa 1984 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Obituary and biographical sketch, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Armistead Lee memoirs, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "A Mishkid's Homecoming"--Armistead Lee, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Writings
    - "Christian Education", 1978 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Memoirs--incomplete, 1979-1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Some Thoughts on Faith and Belief", 1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "The Elizabeth Bentley Matter", 1983 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "My Family", 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs
    - Family, 1901-1948 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Anking, China, 1922-1923 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Yale / Rhodes scholars, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Portraits, circa 1935 - 1965 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - OSS / military service / Burma, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Employment / China, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Canton / Hong Kong / Kunming, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Bermuda, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Rhodes reunion scrapbook, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Family photographs [born digital] (Box 4A)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
  - Clippings
    - General, 1935-2013 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - HUAC testimony, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - HUAC testimony--photocopies, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Soviet espionage--articles printed by Mark Bradley, 1948-1953 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Academic articles, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- John Lee Papers, 1936-2011; Series II
  Series II consists of the John Lee papers. The correspondence is arranged alphabetically and is predominantly email exchanges between John Lee and his family members on Duncan Chaplin Lee. Correspondents also include historians and scholars of Cold War espionage such as Nigel West, Brian Loring Villa, and Allen Weinstein. A sizable portion of Series II includes copies of FBI files on Duncan Chaplin Lee obtained by or given to John Lee by Mark Bradley or Bruce Craig. In addition to the FBI files, the research materials contain book reviews, academic essays, excerpts from books, magazine articles, and assorted published material that suggest Chaplin Lee was a spy for the Soviet Union.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1999-2010 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bradley, Mark, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Craig, Bruce, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - H-Diplo letter and controversy, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Lee, Armistead, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Lee, Eleanore, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - New York Times, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Smith, Arnold, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Villa, Brian Loring, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Weinstein, Allen, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - West, Nigel, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Research Materials
    - Documents from Mark Bradley--FBI files and Yale transcripts on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1935-2010 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Copies and transcripts of Duncan Chaplin Lee letters, 1936-1937 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Notes and transcriptions by Mark Bradley on Duncan Chaplin Lee letters, 1937-2010 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Venona decrypts, 1942-1999 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Copies of correspondence with Yale University, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Biographical material and clippings on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1943-1951 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - FBI files--Elizabeth Bentley interview, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Copies of grand jury transcripts, 1947-1999 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - FBI Files on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1949-1956 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    - FBI Files on Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1949-1956 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and FBI Files on Duncan Chaplin Lee (copies), 1949-1956 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Elizabeth Bentley--Out of Bondage, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Documents on Duncan Chaplin Lee from Bruce Craig, 1952-1999 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Freedom of Information Act requests by Mark Bradley, 1952-2011 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Freedom of Information Act requests by John Lee, 1955-2003 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Venona cables and Eleanore Lee letter, 1955-2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Jefferson County Historical Society at Leeland, 1998 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Published materials on communism and Soviet espionage, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Accusations against Duncan Chaplin Lee, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Nigel West, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "Red Scare bibliography", circa 1999 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Duncan Lee chronology, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Draft of chapter 2--"A Very Principled Boy", 2010 (Box 8, Folder 14)